Guide to the Elizabeth Barlow Rogers Papers 1906-2020 (bulk 1960s-2010s) MS 3206
New-York Historical Society
Elizabeth Barlow Rogers papers
1906-2020 (bulk 1960s-2010s)
New-York Historical Society
Rogers, Elizabeth Barlow, 1936-
MS 3206
19.32 Linear feet in 14 record cartons, 1 legal manuscript box, 1 flat box, and 1 medium-oversized flat file.
16.5 Gigabytes in 707 digital files, including 36 audiovisual files that total approximately 8 hours in duration.
This collection documents the life and work of Elizabeth Barlow Rogers, a landscape architect and parks advocate. Rogers published several monographs on New York environmental history and landscape design, as well as multiple articles on urban renewal and history. She was appointed Central Park Administrator by Mayor Ed Koch in 1979 and was a founding member and president of the Central Park Conservancy in 1980; she retired from both positions in 1995. Her papers illustrate the breadth of her career and public life as well as the physical, economic, and social changes that New York underwent since the 1970s. Materials include manuscripts, published materials, photos and audiovisual material, and correspondence.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series and subseries:
Series I. Written Works and Materials, 1962-2020
Subseries I.A Drafts and Research, 1962-2020
Subseries I.B Press and Reviews, 1969-2018
Series II. Professional Papers and Central Park Conservancy Records, 1962-2019
Subseries II.A Official Publications, 1973-2015
Subseries II.B Publicity and Correspondence, 1971-2019
Subseries II.C Advocacy, 1962-2019
Subseries II.D Graphic Materials and Audiovisual Materials, 1968-2011
Series III. Teaching Materials and Lectures, 1964-2007
Series IV. Awards and Memorabilia, 1906-2017
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Barlow Rogers (born 1936) is a prominent architectural and landscape historian, conservationist, and urban advocate. She is a former administrator of Central Park (1979-1995) and is a lifetime trustee of the Central Park Conservancy (CPC), which she helped establish in 1980. She also founded the Central Park Taskforce in 1975. Rogers served as the President of the CPC from 1980-1995. The goals of the Central Park Conservancy include revitalizing the physical infrastructure of the park, reorienting its goals and management, and expanding the role of the park in New York City civic life. The CPC is a public-private partnership which brings private philanthropic funds into the service of maintaining and providing a public good or service; it was one of the first forms of public-private partnership established by then-Mayor Ed Koch in 1980. Since then, public-private partnerships like the CPC have been replicated throughout New York City.
Rogers was selected for the dual role of Central Park Administrator and CPC President due to her history of advocacy and passion for civic engagement. Further, she was an accomplished writer and expert on parks, landscape design, and New York environmental history. Her publishing career includes titles such as The Forests and Wetlands of New York City (New York: Little, Brown, 1971), for which she won a John Burroughs Medal, Frederick Law Olmsted's New York (New York: Whitney Museum/Praeger, 1972), The Central Park Book (Central Park Task Force, 1977), Rebuilding Central Park: A Management and Restoration Plan (MIT Press, 1987), and her self-described magnum opus Landscape Design: A Cultural and Architectural History (New York: Abrams, 2001). All of her book projects in the collection are surrounded by contextual research, manuscripts in various stages, feedback from experts in the field, and correspondence with publishers and advocates. Her expertise on New York and Central Park is contextualized in a wider philosophical and historical framework of space and place and the relationship between humans and their built environments; this theme undergirds her civic and professional work as well as her personal papers.
Rogers also taught courses on landscape design and history at several institutions in New York. Her teaching materials are similarly robust and help illustrate her academic achievements as well as her passion for sharing landscape history beyond the park. Her teaching materials are geographically diverse, demonstrating her wide range of knowledge. She collaborated with multiple parks officials and scholars within the United States and abroad in Europe and Asia. She has continued to advocate for landscape studies; her Foundation of Landscape Studies was integrated into the University of Virginia's Landscape Studies Initiative in 2017.
In her early life, Rogers wrote poetry and speculative historical fiction based on her enjoyment of the New York environment and her interest in New York history. She attended Wellesley College and maintains a close relationship with the institution; she assisted the College in developing plans for the renewal of their campus grounds and has received awards and recognition as an outstanding alumna. She received her Masters degree from Yale University in city planning in 1964 and moved permanently to New York City shortly after. Her social circle includes other members of New York civil society. She maintained close ties with public figures and has been celebrated by numerous organizations for her contributions to New York City.
Access Restrictions
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth Barlow Rogers in 2008 and 2021.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes a wide array of oversized, photographic, audiovisual, and ephemeral material. The bulk of the papers are Rogers' manuscripts and writing materials, both published and unpublished. Her monographs such as Landscape Design: A Cultural and Architectural History (New York: Harry N. Abrams, 2001) and The Forests and Wetlands of New York City (New York: Little, Brown, 1971) appear in finished form, surrounded by drafts, research, and correspondence that sketch the writing process from start to finish. The related correspondence, publicity, and press present a full picture of her writing career and research achievements.
Rogers' personal life is not well documented in the collection. She was born in San Antonio, Texas to C. L. and Elizabeth Browning. Her husband, Theodore C. Rogers, and her children appear in photographs at special events. There are some written materials from her two brothers and parents, especially related to her early work as a research aide to New York State Senator, Whitney North Seymour Jr.
The collection also houses important documents, photographs, and publications around Rogers' career in the NYC Parks Department and her founding of the Central Park Conservancy (CPC). Materials include reports, outreach, and correspondence with collaborators in city government, New York society, and the global parks administration community. Her public life is well documented through speeches, photographs, correspondence, press, and awards. Many notable civic and artistic individuals appear in Rogers' photographs and correspondence including Robert Moses, Ed Koch, George H.W. Bush, Yoko Ono, and Brooke Astor. She was part of civic movements across New York City that responded to the fiscal crisis of the 1970s and the ensuing revitalization and urban renewal efforts of public-private partnerships.
Another key aspect of the collection is Rogers' teaching materials, which often have a global focus that expands the research scope of the collection to outside New York. Rogers taught courses on landscape design and architecture, garden history, and New York environmental history at institutions such as Columbia University, the Cooper Union, Bard Graduate Center, and the New York Botanical Garden. She also established programs of study in Landscape Studies at Bard Graduate Center and founded the Center for Landscape Studies. In addition to coursework, lecture notes, and planning materials, there is a notable spread of clippings and periodicals that mention Rogers or her institutional affiliations.
Many items in the collection have been labeled by the donor prior to gifting the material to N-YHS. There are multiple instances where Rogers has annotated documents and objects with notes that describe their context or relevance to her life and work. These have always been preserved with the material and are also reflected in the arrangement and description of the collection.
There are also 3 CDs, 5 DVDs, and 9 VHS tapes across the collection that hold documentaries, interviews, and recordings from Rogers' events and speeches. Finally, there are oversized materials that include architectural designs and blueprints for Central Park projects, large photographs, and printed ephemera.
Blueprints (reprographic copies); Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Correspondence.; East Hampton (N.Y.); Environment & policy.; Environmental protection.; Forested wetlands.; Fund raising -- New York (State) -- New York.; Landscape architecture.; Landscape design.; Landscape gardening.; Manuscripts (documents); Municipal government -- New York (State) -- New York.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographs.; Public-private sector cooperation.; Urban landscape architecture.; Urban renewal -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women civic leaders -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women in community development -- New York (State) -- New York.; Astor, Brooke; Central Park Conservancy (New York, N.Y.); Central Park Task Force; Davidson, Bruce, 1933-; Koch, Ed, 1924-2013; Olmsted, Frederick Law, 1822-1903; Orkin, Ruth; Seymour, Whitney North, Jr., 1923-2019
- Series I. Written Works and Materials, 1962-2020
  Scope and Contents
  Series I covers Elizabeth Barlow Rogers' academic and publishing career from her early work, unpublished in graduate school (circa 1962) to her contemporary books and articles (circa 2020). Accompanying the drafts and manuscripts are research files, correspondence with colleagues and publishers, publishing layouts with photos and illustrations, and press materials.
  Arrangement
  The Series is divided into three subseries by format:
  Subseries I.A Drafts and Research, 1962-2020
  Subseries I.B Press and Reviews, 1969-2018
  - Subseries I.A Drafts and Research, 1962-2020
    Subseries I.a Drafts and Research (1962-2020) covers both Elizabeth Barlow Rogers' major publications and her personal literary projects. In addition to multiple drafts and revised versions of manuscripts, Subseries I.a also includes design and layout materials including original photographs and illustrations. Another significant feature of Subseries I.a are the published copies of Rogers' books and essays. Rogers often kept the entirety of the periodical that she or her articles appeared in, so folders are sometimes identified by title of publication rather than specific work. Rogers also maintained research files on New York history, architecture, and design. These files include both domestic and international literature and ephemera.
    The arrangement of Subseries I.a closely follows the original order of the material as it was received from the donor. Some materials that were originally grouped or tied together by the donor have been broken up into smaller sections and put into multiple, consecutive folders. When the connection between the materials in the original order was particularly emphasized by the donor, a note was added to the finding aid on the item level to indicate this. In some cases, folders have been reordered from their original order to numerical order in order to promote ease of access (e.g., Folders containing numbered chapters were rearranged to be in ascending order).
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City, Inwood Chapter Research, 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jamaica Bay Research, 1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Manuscripts of The Forests and Wetlands of New York City (1 of 2), circa 1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Manuscripts of The Forests and Wetlands of New York City (2 of 2), circa 1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Swallows of Staten Island, 1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Manuscripts of Early Chapters of The Forests and Wetlands of New York City, circa 1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Research for The Forests and Wetlands of New York City, Alley Pond Park, 1957-1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Jamaica Bay Chapter Typescripts and Research, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City, Colonial Landscape, 1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Manuscripts, Introduction, Geneology, Inwood Hill, Pelham Bay, circa 1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Chapter Drafts (1 of 2), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Chapter Drafts (2 of 2), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - General Park Photos by EBR, 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Manuscripts, circa 1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - Publishing Correspondence, Julian Bach, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Original Photos Taken by EBR for The Forests and Wetlands of New York City, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - Pelham Bay Park Photos by EBR for The Forests and Wetlands of New York City, circa 1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    - Photos by EBR for The Forests and Wetlands of New York City, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Welfare Island Photos and Correspondence, circa 1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Business Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Introduction, circa 1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Draft, circa 1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Original Manuscripts, 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City (Monograph), 1969, 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
    - The Forests and Wetlands of New York City Research Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
      The materials in Box 2 Folders 1-5 were tied together with red ribbon by the donor. They are arranged it the same order that they were received in.
    - Charles McLaughlin Thesis on Frederick Law Olmsted (3 folders), 1960 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2-4)
      The materials in Box 2 Folders 1-5 were originally tied together with red ribbon by the donor. According to EBR, McLaughlin gave her this copy of his thesis, "Selected Letters of Frederick Law Olmsted," in response to her research for her book Frederick Law Olmsted's New York.
    - Manuscript for "Golden Eagle" (TV episode), 1973 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
      The materials in Box 2 Folders 1-5 were originally tied together with red ribbon by the donor.
    - Wainscott Journal, 1973 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    - Research Notes For Frederick Law Olmsted's New York, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    - East Hampton History Research Materials, circa 1962-1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    - East Hampton: A History and Guide (1 of 3), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - East Hampton: A History and Guide (2 of 3), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
    - East Hampton: A History and Guide (3 of 3), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    - East Hampton: A History and Guide Chapter Manuscripts (2 of 2), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12 a)
      The materials in Box 2 Folders 12-15 were tied together with green ribbon by the donor.
    - East Hampton: A History and Guide Chapter Manuscripts (1 of 2), circa 1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - East Hampton: A History and Guide (monograph), 1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    - East Hampton: A History and Guide Research (1 of 2), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    - East Hampton: A History and Guide Research (2 of 2), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
      The materials in Box 2 Folders 12-15 were tied together with ribbon by the donor.
    - Unpublished Manuscript for a Biography of Frederick Law Olmsted (1 of 2), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
    - Unpublished Manuscript for a Biography of Frederick Law Olmsted (2 of 2), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    - Frederick Law Olmsted's New York (monograph), 1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
      The materials in Box 2 Folders 18-22 were tied together with green ribbon by the donor.
    - Frederick Law Olmsted's New York Clippings and Sesquicentennial, 1972-1977 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
      The materials from Box 2 Folders 18-22 were tied together with green ribbon by the donor.
    - Frederick Law Olmsted's New York Draft (1 of 3), circa 1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
    - Frederick Law Olmsted's New York Draft (2 of 3), circa 1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Frederick Law Olmsted's New York Draft (3 of 3), circa 1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    - Frederick Law Olmsted's New York Draft Copy 2, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    - Frederick Law Olmsted's New York Correspondence and Contract, 1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    - Olmsted Op-ed Article and First Chapter of Typescript for Frederick Law Olmsted's New York, 1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    - Elizabeth Barlow Rogers' Research Notes for Frederick Law Olmsted's New York, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    - Important Correspondence for Frederick Law Olmsted's New York, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Original Images for The Central Park Book (1 of 3), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    - Original Images for The Central Park Book (2 of 3), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    - Original Images for The Central Park Book (3 of 3), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
    - Unpublished Manuscripts of The Annotated Diary of Eliza Bellamy, 1972 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - Drafts and Research for Eliza Bellamy (1 of 2), circa 1970, 2020 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    - Drafts and Research for Eliza Bellamy (2 of 2), circa 1970, 2020 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    - Nature in New York (film) Correspondence, 1975 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    - Nature in New York (film) Manuscripts, 1975 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Unpublished Essays, circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
      Essays include: "Tidewater Hudson"; "How Green Was My City"; "The Public Park: A Brief History"; Pelham Bay and Nature Study"
    - "Texas Hill Country" (essay), circa 1960s, 1971 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
      Includes among other materials notes from Elizabeth Barlow Rogers' visit with President Lyndon B. Johnson and First Lady Claudia "Lady Bird" Johnson in their Texas home, possibly during or shorly after Johnson's term as President.
    - "Sacred to Memory" (essay), 1993 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence and Essay Samples for New York Newsday, 1988 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    - Research Materials for Essay on Greenwood Cemetery, 2002, 2007-2008 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    - Autobiographical Fragment, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches, 1989-2012 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
      Includes speeches from the New York Society Library and EBR exhibition; the publication of Writing the Garden: A Literary Conversation Across Two Centuries (2011); "Sacred to Memory"; "The Public Park: A Brief History"; adult education talks in the Arsenal Gallery; and "Discovering the Park: Its Southern Sections" fieldtrip.
    - Genealogy - Eastern Long Island, circa 1960s-1970s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Central Park Book (monography), 1977 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
    - Articles By Others Saved By Elizabeth Barlow Rogers, 1978-2020 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
    - Elizabeth Barlow Rogers' Term Papers From The Yale School of City Planning, 1962-1964 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
    - Autobiographical Fragment and Resumes, 1971 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
    - Elizabeth Barlow Rogers Articles and Research on Robert Moses, 1951-2007 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    - Research and Manuscripts for South Street Seaport Article, 1971 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    - Southampton - NY's Newest Suburb?, 1973 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    - Materials for Review of The Vanishing Wetlands, 1962-1971 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    - NY Mag Teach-In Conference on the Environment, 1970 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    - NY Mag Article "The Experiment in Environmental Living", 1971 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    - Published Photos of the South Street Seaport, 1971 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    - Joan Rosner's Operation Jamaica Bay and Letter to EBR, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
    - NY Mag Jamaica Bay Article and Correspondence, 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
      Correspondence from Robert Moses to Elizabeth Barlow Rogers praising her article on Jamaica Bay. Also, a very critical letter from a reader who disagrees with EBR's interpretation.
    - Manuscript Drafts and Materials for NY Mag "Environmental Teach-in", 1970 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1970, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
      Some materials relate to EBR's ongoing relationship with New York Magazine.
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 2 no. 49, 1969 December 8 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 3 no. 13, 1970 March 30 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 4 no. 3, 1971 January 18 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 4 no. 48, 1971 November 29 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 5 no. 22, 1972 May 29 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 8 no. 9, 1975 March 3 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 9 no. 24, 1976 June 14 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 9 no. 31, 1976 August 2 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
    - NY Mag EBR Article V. 16 no. 23, 1983 June 6 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    - Smithsonian EBR Article EBR Article V. 1 no. 11, 1971 February (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
    - Smithsonian EBR Article EBR Article V. 2 no. 5, 1971 August (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
    - The New Criterion EBR Review V. 22 no. 3, 2002 November (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
    - The New Criterion EBR Review V. 23 no. 2, 2004 October (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
    - The New Criterion EBR Review V. 23 no. 9, 2005 May (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
    - The New Criterion EBR Review V. 24 no. 8, 2006 April (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
    - The New Criterion EBR Review V. 29 no. 7, 2011 March (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
    - The New Criterion EBR Review V. 30 no. 1, 2011 September (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28)
    - The New Criterion EBR Review V. 35 no. 1, 2016 September (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
    - Bulletin of the German History Institute EBR Article, 2007 September 4 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
    - Monuments Historiques EBR French Language Article no. 173, 1991 March-April (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - Decorative Arts (Bard Graduate Center) V. IX no. 1, 2001 Fall-2002 Winter (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
    - Arnoldia EBR Excerpt V. 69 no. 4, 2012 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 33)
    - View EBR Article no. 15, 2015 Summer (Offsite-box 4, Folder 34)
    - Audubon EBR Article V. 73 no. 2, 1971 March (Offsite-box 4, Folder 35)
    - Good Design and the Dressed Down and Branded City, 2002 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    - A Place of Memory (Central Park Conservancy), circa 1986 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    - iFatti Anno 12 no. 43, 2007 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    - Approach Spring, 2007 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Published Printed Matter, 1969, 1997, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    - Landscape Design: A Cultural and Architectural History (monograph), 2001 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)